## Kirsten Scarlett Evonuk

Postdoctoral Fellow, Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute

#### Institutional Address

Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute 9500 Euclid Ave.

NC30

Cleveland, OH 44195

#### **Institutional Email**

evonuks@ccf.org

#### **Personal Email**

ksevonuk@gmail.com

#### **Personal Website**

https://www.ksevonuk.com

#### LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/kirstenevonuk/

#### **ORCID**

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2750-0289

#### ORCID iD QR Code



Dedicated scientist with 8+ years of experience conducting neuroimmunological research on mechanisms underlying autoimmune neuroinflammatory disease. Successful record of grant funding with 4 first-authored, peer-reviewed publications demonstrating dedication to research in neuroinflammation and multiple sclerosis. Expertise in molecular biology techniques, immunohistochemistry and imaging, utilization of *in vivo* models, *ex vivo* and *in vitro* calcium imaging, and rodent behavioral analyses. Teacher and mentor to students of all levels, with ability to teach laboratory techniques and explain complicated subjects in an understandable way. Seeking a career as a tenure track professor and primary investigator to study pathophysiology of multiple sclerosis.

## **Education**

03/2016 PhD in Neurobiology

**Department of Neurobiology** 

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

Dissertation title: "The role of glutamate in immune cell infiltration and

excitotoxic mechanisms in autoimmune demyelination"

PhD mentor: Tara M. DeSilva, PhD

05/2011 **BA in Psychology** 

**Department of Psychology** 

University of Portland, Portland, OR

Graduated summa cum laude

**Minor:** Biology

Thesis title: "Effects of Social and Enriched Environments on Recovery

from Medial Frontal Cortex Contusion in a Rat Model"

Thesis supervisor: Jeffrey Smith, PhD

## **Professional Appointments**

### 2016-present Postdoctoral Fellow

**Department of Neurosciences** 

Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland, OH

Advisor: Tara M. DeSilva, PhD

Demonstrated that deletion of a subunit of the AMPA-type glutamate receptor on mature oligodendrocytes confers protection to myelin and axons in an animal model of multiple sclerosis. This work resulted in a peer-reviewed publication in *AAAS Science Advances*. Postdoctoral work was funded through a 1-year Cole Eye Institute Vision Science Training Program T32 and a 3-year NMSS Postdoctoral Fellowship. Mentored 2 undergraduate students and 1 high school student in the DeSilva laboratory.

#### 2012-2016 **Graduate Research Trainee**

**Department of Neurobiology** 

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

Advisor: Tara M. DeSilva, PhD

Demonstrated amelioration of an animal model of multiple sclerosis by blocking the system  $x_c^-$  glutamate/cystine transporter using pharmacological and genetic methods. Published 3 peer-reviewed, first-author papers resulting from graduate research efforts. Graduate work was funded through a 2-year Immunologic Diseases and Basic Immunology T32. Mentored 4 summer research undergraduate students in the DeSilva laboratory for 10-week laboratory experiences.

## **Publications**

### **Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles**

- Evonuk, K. S., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Thornell, I. M., Adler, K., Bingaman, A. M., Bevensee, M. O., Weaver, C. T., Min, B., DeSilva, T. M. (2020). Reduction of AMPA receptor activity on mature oligodendrocytes attenuates loss of myelinated axons in autoimmune neuroinflammation. *Sci Adv.* 6(2): eaax5936. doi: 10.1126/sciadv.aax5936. PMID: 31934627; PMCID: PMC6949032
- 2. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Prabhu, S. D., Young, M. E., DeSilva, T. M. (2017). Myocardial Ischemia/Reperfusion impairs neurogenesis and hippocampal-dependent learning and memory. *Brain Behav Immun*. 61: 266-273. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2016.09.001. PMID: 27600185; PMCID: PMC5511033
- 3. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Moseley, C. E., Doyle, R. E., Weaver, C. T., DeSilva, T. M. (2016). Determining immune system suppression versus CNS protection for pharmacological interventions in autoimmune demyelination. *J Vis Exp*. Sep 12;(115). doi: 10.3791/54348. PMID: 27685467; PMCID: PMC5092010
- Evonuk, K. S., Baker, B. J., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Sestero, C. M., Johnston, B. P., De Sarno, P., Tang, A., Gembitsky, I., Hewett, S. J., Weaver, C. T., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. (2015). Inhibition of System Xc(-) Transporter Attenuates Autoimmune Inflammatory Demyelination. *J Immunol*. 195: 450-463. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1401108. PMID: 26071560; PMCID: PMC4490999

## **Awards and Honors**

2019	4th Place Poster Presentation Award, Cleveland Brain Health Initiative
	(CBHI) 2019 Annual Retreat, Case Western Reserve University,
	Cleveland, OH
2018	Alumni Association Career Development Postdoctoral Fellow Award,
	Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH
2018	Travel Award, European Committee for Treatment and Research in
	Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS)
2018	Neurosciences Oral Presentation Award, Cleveland Clinic Neurological
	Institute Research Day, Cleveland Clinic, OH

2018	Best Young Investigator Oral Presentation (2nd place), Americas Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ACTRIMS)
2018	Educational Travel Grant, Americas Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ACTRIMS)
2015	<b>Data Blitz Presentation Award</b> , Comprehensive Neuroscience Center Retreat, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL
2014	Travel Fellowship, American Society for Neurochemistry
2014	<b>Travel Grant</b> , University of Alabama at Birmingham Graduate Student Association
2014	<b>2nd Place Poster Presentation Award</b> , Comprehensive Neuroscience Center Neuroscience Research Day, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL
2013	1st Place Data Blitz Presentation, Comprehensive Neuroscience Center Retreat, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

## **Grants and Fellowships**

2019-2022	"Selective deletion of AMPA-type glutamate receptors on
	oligodendrocytes is neuroprotective in autoimmune demyelination."

NMSS Postdoctoral Fellowship, FG-1807-31882

\$188,067

Role: Principal Investigator

2017-2018 Cole Eye Institute Vision Science Training Program

NIH/NEI T32, T32 EY24236-2

Principal Investigators: Bela Anand-Apte and Joe Gilbert Hollyfield

\$43,692

Role: Trainee

2014-2016 Immunologic Diseases and Basic Immunology T32

NIH/NIAID T32, T32 Al7051-38 and T32 Al7051-37 Principal Investigator: Harry William Schroeder

\$40,812

Role: Trainee

## **Presentations**

### **Contributed Talks**

- Evonuk, K. S., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Thornell, I. M., Adler, K., Bingaman, A. M., Bevensee, M. O., Weaver, C. T., Min, B., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective reduction of AMPA receptors on mature oligodendrocytes prevents demyelination and axonal injury in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis." ECTRIMS Congress 2018, Berlin, Germany (October 11, 2018).
- 2. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective Deletion of AMPA Receptors on Oligodendrocytes Prevents Demyelination and Axonal Injury in Autoimmune Demyelination." ACTRIMS Forum 2018, San Diego, California (February 1, 2018; <u>Best Young Investigator Oral Presentation 2<sup>nd</sup> place</u>).
- 3. **Evonuk, K. S**, Baker, B. J., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Sestero, C. M., Johnston, B. P., De Sarno, P., Tang, A., Gembitsky, I., Hewett, S. J., Weaver, C. T., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "Inhibition of system Xc- transporter attenuates autoimmune inflammatory demyelination." Multiple Sclerosis Research Symposium, University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama (June 4, 2015).

## **Campus Talks**

1. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Thornell, I. M., Adler, K., Bingaman, A. M., Bevensee, M. O., Weaver, C. T., Min, B., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective reduction of AMPA receptors on mature oligodendrocytes prevents demyelination and axonal injury in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis." Cleveland Clinic Neurological Institute Research Day, Cleveland, Ohio (May 24, 2018; received <u>Neurosciences Oral Presentation Award</u>).

## **Posters**

- 1. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective Reduction of AMPA Receptors on Oligodendrocytes Prevents Demyelination and Axonal Injury in Autoimmune Demyelination." National Multiple Sclerosis Society Tykeson Fellows Conference, Atlanta, Georgia (November 14 and 15, 2019).
- 2. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective Deletion of AMPA Receptors on Oligodendrocytes Prevents Demyelination and Axonal Injury in Autoimmune Demyelination." Case Western University Cleveland Brain Health Initiative (CBHI) 2019 Annual Retreat, Cleveland, Ohio (August 26, 2019; 4th place presentation).

- 3. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective Deletion of AMPA Receptors on Oligodendrocytes Prevents Demyelination and Axonal Injury in Autoimmune Demyelination." Poster#: P194. ACTRIMS Forum 2018, San Diego, California (February 2, 2018). https://doi.org/10.1177/1352458517750967
- 4. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective deletion of AMPA receptors on oligodendrocytes prevents axonal injury in autoimmune demyelination." Poster#: T14-110A. XIII European Meeting on Glial Cells in Health and Disease, Edinburgh, United Kingdom (July 10, 2017). https://doi.org/10.1002/glia.23157
- Evonuk, K. S., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Monyer, H., DeSilva, T. M. "Selective deletion of AMPA receptors on oligodendrocytes prevents excitotoxicity in EAE." Program#/Poster#: 511.06/U18. Society for Neuroscience Poster Session, San Diego, California (November 15, 2016).
- Evonuk, K. S., Baker, B. J., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Sestero, C. M., Johnston, B. P., De Sarno, P., Tang, A., Gembitsky, I., Hewett, S. J., Sontheimer, H., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "System xc- transporter modulates CNS infiltration of immune cells and reactive gliosis in autoimmune inflammatory disease." 4<sup>th</sup> Southeastern Immunology Symposium, Atlanta, Georgia (June 13, 2015).
- Evonuk, K. S., Baker, B. J., Doyle, R. E., Moseley, C. E., Sestero, C. M., Johnston, B. P., De Sarno, P., Tang, A., Gembitsky, I., Hewett, S. J., Sontheimer, H., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "System xc- transporter modulates CNS infiltration of immune cells and reactive gliosis in autoimmune inflammatory disease." Poster#: PSM03-17. American Society for Neurochemistry 46<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting. Atlanta. Georgia (March 16, 2015).
- 8. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Baker, B. J., Doyle, R. E., Sestero, C. M., Johnston, B. P., De Sarno, P., Tang, A., Gembitsky, I., Hewett, S. J., Sontheimer, H., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "System Xc- transporter modulates CNS infiltration of immune cells in autoimmune inflammatory disease." Program#/Poster#: 223.11/G12. Society for Neuroscience Poster Session, Washington, D. C. (November 16, 2014).
- 9. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Baker, J., Sestero, C. M., Doyle, R. E., Timberlake, M. A., Sontheimer, H., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "System xc- inhibition improves histopathological and clinical outcomes in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis." University of Alabama at Birmingham Comprehensive Neuroscience Center Neuroscience Research Day, Birmingham, Alabama (February 7, 2014; 2nd place presentation).

- Evonuk, K. S., Baker, J., Sestero, C. M., Doyle, R. E., Timberlake, M. A., Sontheimer, H., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "System xc- inhibition improves histopathological and clinical outcomes in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis." Program#/Poster#: 441.09/Z11. Society for Neuroscience Meeting, San Diego, California (November 11, 2013).
- 11. **Evonuk, K. S.**, Baker, B. J., Sestero, C. M., Doyle, R. E., Timberlake, M. A., Raman, C., DeSilva, T. M. "Inflammatory signaling associated with multiple sclerosis causes excitotoxicity to oligodendrocytes." University of Alabama at Birmingham Multiple Sclerosis Symposium, Birmingham, Alabama (May 16, 2013).

# **Teaching Experience**

03/25/2019

# Guest Lecturer, Pōmaikaʻi Elementary School, Kahului, HI 2<sup>nd</sup> grade class

Developed and delivered a day-long course on cells and neurons, and brain health and safety. Activities included anatomical labeling of neurons and creation of neuron models, creation of a neuronal circuit using neuron models, and a safety-focused egg drop experiment.

06/06/2015

# Guest Lecturer, University of Alabama at Birmingham Center for Pediatric Onset Demyelinating Disease (CPODD) Family Retreat, Birmingham, AL

#### Family education session

The CPODD Family Retreat is an annual camp for children with multiple sclerosis/neuromyelitis optica and their families. Delivered an hour-long lecture to adult family members on the role of oligodendrocytes in the central nervous system, and pathophysiology associated with demyelinating diseases. Lecture included modeling of the myelin sheath on axons and a question-and-answer session.

05/07/2015

# Guest Lecturer, Pōmaikaʻi Elementary School, Kahului, HI 2<sup>nd</sup> grade class

Developed and delivered a day-long course on brain anatomy, and brain health and safety. Activities included creation of brain models and anatomical labeling of brain regions, and a safety-focused egg drop experiment.

03/04/2015

Guest Lecturer, National MS Society Alabama-Mississippi Chapter, Town Village-Vestavia Hills, AL Course: Mood and Cognition in MS

Delivered a two hour-long lecture on mood and cognition in multiple sclerosis (MS), with emphasis on how mood and cognition change in MS and strategies to manage those changes. Students included patients and family members with MS, and residents of Town Village-Vestavia Hills.

07/18/2014

Guest Lecturer, University of Alabama at Birmingham Center for Community OutReach Development (CORD) Summer Science Institute, Birmingham, AL

**Course:** Advanced Principles of Molecular Biology and Neuroscience Developed and delivered a one hour lecture to high school students on basics of neuroscience, including neuronal anatomy and function, and roles of glia in health and disease.

## **Mentoring Experience**

\*indicates mentee authorship on a publication resulting from mentorship

06/2019-present Mentor for Sophia Laye, Hathaway Brown high school

student

Current status: High school junior at Hathaway Brown School

06/2019-present Mentor for Amanda Bingaman, Post-baccalaureate

Readiness Instruction for bioMedical Education (PRIME)

student

Current status: Post-baccalaureate student in the Case Western

Reserve University PRIME certificate program

06/2016-08/2016 Mentor for Keith Adler\*, Kenyon College undergraduate

student

Current status: Research technician at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute

06/2016-08/2016 Mentor for Amanda Bingaman\*, Vanderbilt University

undergraduate student

Current status: Post-baccalaureate student in the Case Western Reserve University Post-baccalaureate Readiness Instruction for

bioMedical Education (PRIME) certificate program

08/2015-11/2015	Mentor for Karen Balcazar, University of Alabama at Birmingham rotation student Current status: Research associate at Xencor
06/2015-08/2015	Mentor for Keith Adler, University of Alabama at Birmingham's Summer Program in Neuroscience (SPIN) undergraduate student  Current status: Research technician at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute
06/2014-08/2014	Mentor for Katie Valin, University of Alabama at Birmingham's Summer Program in Neuroscience (SPIN) undergraduate student Current status: Research assistant at the University of Alabama at Birmingham
08/2013-09/2014	Mentor for Nicole Ogle, University of Alabama at Birmingham undergraduate student Current status: Registered nurse (RN) at St. Vincent's Hospital, Birmingham, AL
06/2012-08/2014	Mentor for Ryan Doyle*, University of Alabama at Birmingham undergraduate student Current status: Registered nurse (RN) at St. Vincent's Hospital, Birmingham, AL
06/2012-08/2012	Mentor for Matthew Timberlake, University of Alabama at Birmingham's Summer Program in Neuroscience (SPIN) undergraduate student  Current status: Postdoctoral scholar at University of California, Davis

# **Outreach and Service**

Walk MS Research Educator
National Multiple Sclerosis Society, Birmingham, AL
Brain Awareness Week Co-Coordinator University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL
Brain Awareness Week Planning Committee Member

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

03/09/2013 and Poster Judge

03/01/2014 Central Alabama Regional Science and Engineering Fair

08/2012-10/2012 Art of Giving Charity Art Auction Volunteer

University of Alabama at Birmingham Research Civitan Club

08/3/2012 Poster Judge

University of Alabama at Birmingham Center for Community Outreach

**Development Summer Science Programs** 

03/19/2012 Brain Awareness Week Demonstration Volunteer

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

## **Professional Service**

Ad hoc reviewer for: Scientific Reports

02/29/2020 Young Investigator Co-Chair

Americas Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis

(ACTRIMS) 2020 Forum "CNS Cellular Networks in MS" session

11/2019-present Communications Team Member

Cleveland Clinic Lerner Postdoctoral Association (LPDA)

11/15/2019 **Session Co-Chair** 

National Multiple Sclerosis Society Tykeson Fellows Conference

"Myelin Repair Vs. Neuroprotection" session

04/2019-11/2019 Conference Planning Committee Member

National Multiple Sclerosis Society Tykeson Fellows Conference

08/2016-present Data on the Table Organizing Committee Member

Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland, OH

2013-2016 Scientific Communication and Innovation (SCI) Talks:

Science Talks for the Community Organizing Committee

Member

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

# **Professional Development**

12/2016 ExCyte Flow Cytometry Training

Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH

08/2015 Advanced Course in Immunology

The American Association of Immunologists

Summer 2015 **Teaching and Learning Course** 

Center for the Integration of Research, Teaching and Learning at

University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, AL

## **Professional Societies**

2014-present American Society for Neurochemistry

2012-present Society for Neroscience

2009-present Psi Chi, The International Honor Society in Psychology